"Saffron for Treating Age-Related
Macular Degeneration"
In addition to two
to three daily servings
of green leafy vegetables,
berries are considered
a healthy choice
for the preservation
of eye health.
As we age, our critical
retinal pigment epithelium layer
starts to break down.
However, we may be able
to decelerate that aging
with blueberries.
Human RPE cells bathed in
blueberry anthocyanins
had fewer free radicals
and a lower proportion
of aged cells,
suggesting that blueberries
and other red, blue, and purple
pigmented fruits and vegetables
may help prevent age-related
macular degeneration.
Protective properties
have also been demonstrated
in vitro on RPE cells
from purple
sweet potato anthocyanin
as well as the yellow pigment
in turmeric and an amla extract
(Indian gooseberry).
However, the only
human interventional trials
on berries for vision
were a month-long trial
of a bilberry extract
that demonstrated
significantly less eye strain
after iPad use
compared to placebo
and a study showing
three weeks of blueberry juice
or freeze-dried blueberry powder
both significantly improved
photostress recovery time,
which is the time needed
to recuperate visual acuity
after bright light exposure
by about five seconds.
Only one pigmented food
has been put to the test
in macular
degeneration patients:
the spice saffron.
Saffron is so potent
that the whole spice
can be stuffed into capsules
to pit them head-to-head
against placebo.
Those with early-stage
age-related macular degeneration
were randomized to a tiny pinch
(20 mg, about 8 threads)
of saffron versus placebo
for three months.
Compared to the placebo group,
the saffron group experienced
a significant improvement
in retinal flicker sensitivity--
that’s our ability to pick out
high frequency light pulses
(rather than seeing
the flickering light
as a steady beam)
that diminishes with age.
It’s a sensitive test
of retinal function,
but it is of questionable
clinical value.
However, there was
a small improvement
in visual acuity in 80 percent
of the saffron subjects
(being able to see one line
further down on an eye chart)
versus none improving
in the placebo group.
This is particularly important
for those with age-related
macular degeneration
for whom vision tends
to get worse over time,
not better.
What about a more
substantial pinch?
(50 mg, about 20 threads)
Compared to placebo,
three months of this larger dose
led to a similar
improvement in visual acuity
in macular degeneration
patients, suggesting more
is not necessarily better.
Saffron is the most
expensive spice there is,
selling for about $200
an ounce (28 g),
so being able to get away
with a 20 mg dose
(about 15 cents a day)
rather than a 50 mg dose
(closer to 40 cents a day)
could add up over the long run.
Even smaller doses may work too,
but they just
haven’t been tested.
What about
the tiny pinch over a year
instead of just three months?
Early-stage macular patients
were given 20 mg of saffron
a day for an average
of 14 months
and average visual acuity
improved by two eye chart lines.
They also reported
an improvement in contrast
and color perception,
reading ability,
low-light vision,
and overall quality of life.
The problem is the study
lacked a control group,
so it’s hard to put much stock
in subjective measures
of improvement.
Interestingly, a six-month
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
found no objective
acuity improvement
in either the placebo group
or a 30 mg a day saffron group,
yet reported that the patients
unwittingly in the saffron group
gave subjective reports
of better vision
and general wellbeing.
The researchers suggest
this may be an
antidepressant effect,
and indeed a meta-analysis
of a dozen
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
of saffron for depression
found it beat out placebo
and was found comparable
to antidepressant drugs.
The largest saffron
vision trial to date
was a double-blind,
placebo-controlled
crossover trial
in which 100 older adults
with mild or moderate
age-related macular degeneration
were randomized to 20 mg
of saffron a day
or placebo for three months,
then switched
to the opposite group
for an additional three months.
When on the tiny
daily pinch of saffron
there was a significant,
yet modest improvement
in visual acuity,
and this was the case
for both those on and off
best practice therapy
(the beta-carotene free
AREDS supplementation),
suggesting an additive benefit.